Joseph Arcus

Curriculum Vitae

As a Masters of Urban Planning and Policy candidate at University of Illinois -Chicago, I combine practical work experience with research and analytical skills. My professional roles have given me firsthand insight into urban economic development with a notable focus on sustainability. My research interests focus on urban housing policy and the implementation of sustainability projects.

Contact



💡 Chicago, IL



L 224.805.0044



<u>arcus.joe@gmail.com</u>

jarcus3@uic.edu

Skills

- GIS (ESRI products) Advanced
- MS Access Advanced
- MS Excel Advanced
- SQL Advanced 0
- Adobe Suite (Photoshop, Illustrator, Indesign) - Intermediate
- SPSS Intermediate

Honors and Awards

- Burnham Scholarship, University of Illinois - Chicago (2017-2018)
- DePaul University President's Scholarship (2013-2017)
- J.J. Johnson Scholarship Recipient, Service Employees International Union (2013-2017)
- Eagle Scout, Boy Scouts of America (2014)

Education

Master of Urban Planning and Policy Aug 2018 - Present **University of Illinois - Chicago**

Concentration: Economic Development

Degree in progress

B.A. Environmental Studies & B.A. Geography May 2017 DePaul University, Chicago, IL, U.S.A.

Overall GPA: 3.64/4.00; Major GPA: 3.64/4.00

Graduated Cum Laude

Current Position

Research Assistant

lune 2019 - Present

Natalie P. Voorhees Center for Neighborhood and Community Improvement, University of Illinois - Chicago

- O Graduate-level research assistantship (25% time); tuition waiver.
- O Gather, process, and analyze industry-level data in estimating the Chicago-area clean economy.
- O Research and analyze industry reports from key clean economy sectors including solar and wind energy.
- Gather, process, and map block group-level data on disability and transit access in select American cities.
- O Supervisor: Dr. Janet Smith, Director. 312.996.6336 / <u>janets@uic.edu</u>.

Work Experience

Planning Intern - City of Highland Park, IL (Nov 2018 - August 2019)

- O Graduate level internship, part time.
- O Researched and analyzed land use decisions.
- Research, content creation, and editing role in active transportation plan update, *MoveHP*.
- O Reviewed applications for historic preservation projects and design reviews.
- O Wrote weekly and monthly newsletter articles.
- O Projects included: Researched tax impact of multifamily and industrial land uses; map of bicycle crashes in Highland Park; created a Storymap of historic homes.
- O Supervisor: Mr. Drew Awsumb, Deputy Director. 847.432.0867 / <u>dawsumb@cityhpil.com</u>.

Project Coordinator - Office of Sustainability, City of Knoxville, Tennessee (Aug 2017 - June 2018)

- Year of national service with AmeriCorps.
- Managed energy databases for municipal operations.
- O Analyzed data for Office of Sustainability projects, and assisted in data analysis for other city operations.
- O Projects included: electric bus research, cost forecasting, and grant application; draft city policy on community gardens; management of LED streetlight conversion.
- O Supervisor: Mr. Brian Blackmon, Director. 865.215.4430 / <u>bblackmon@knoxvilletn.gov</u>.

Intern - Mapping Department, Commonwealth Edison (Summer 2016)

- Organized 30,000 files across two interdepartmental drives. Implemented file naming and organization system to ensure continued organization.
- Identified and corrected issues in spatial integrity in metropolitan equipment survey.

Relevant Graduate Coursework

Plan-Making Studio

- Worked as a team to prepare a comprehensive plan for an industrial corridor in Chicago.
- Presented draft plan, created graphics, and assisted in the layout of the plan document.

Economic Development Analysis, I & II

• Theory and practical application of economic development.

Environmental Planning and Policy

• Review of environmental planning, policy, legislation, issues, and programs.

Publications

Fontane, J, Awsumb, D, Cross, A, Jackson, J, **Arcus, J** (*Publication forthcoming*) "*MoveHP*: An Update to Bike-Walk 2030." Department of Community Development, City of Highland Park.

Zafer, S, Smith, J, Kursman, J, **Arcus, J**, Gendel, T, Goodspeed, C (*Publication forthcoming*) "Clean Energy Economy in the Chicago Region and Cook County." Voorhees Center for Neighborhood and Community Improvement, Chicago.